

Masum Islam SENIOR FULL STACK ENGINEER









https://www.linkedin.com/in/masum84/



masum.islam

PROFILE SUMMARY

Extensive international experience in the software industry with 20+ years of experience in several industries and 15+ years of that in Java and Node.Js/Experss.js backend development. Working knowledge & understanding of IT technologies, workflows and processes. Experience developing, designing and evolving software applications. Ambitious problem solver with a passion for telecommunications with 8+ years & digital banking 3+ years of experience in multi-tiered web applications.

Areas of expertise

- Java, Spring , Java EE
- AWS, OpenShift & Azure Cloud Computing
- Azure DevOps
- IDEs, Build tools, SCM
- Jira CI/CD, Jenkins
- SQL DB: Oracle, MySQL, MariaDB, PostgreSQL
- NoSQL DB: MongoDB, DynamoDB
- Agile Methodologies

WORK EXPERIENCE

Geneva, Switzerland Hybrid

Feb 2024 - Nov 2024



Full stack developer

As a senior backend developer at WIPO, I leverage cutting-edge technologies to drive our cloud migration projects. My primary focus is on modernizing and migrating legacy WIPO system, to AWS Cloud.

Technologies: Java 21, Spring boot, Hibernate, Liquibase, Docker, Cucumber, JUnit5, Mockito, RESTful, OpenAPI, SOAP, Angular, AWS API Gateway, Lambda functions, Fargate on EKS, RDS for PostgreSQL, DynamoDB, S3, SQS, CDK by Typescript, IntelliJ, Maven, Git, Jira

Key Responsibilities:

- Specializing in Java Spring Cloud to build robust, scalable backend services.
- Utilizing AWS API Gateway to create, maintain, and secure APIs.
- Cloud Development: Java Spring Cloud for scalable backend services.
- API Management: AWS API Gateway for secure APIs.
- Serverless Computing: AWS Lambda for serverless solutions
- Database Management: Amazon DynamoDB and PostgreSQL RDS.
- Containerization: Amazon ECS for container deployment.
- Storage Solutions: Amazon S3 for secure object storage.
- Auth & Auth: Amazon Cognito for user authentication and authorization.
- Compute Resources: Amazon EC2 management.
- IAM: Secure access with AWS IAM.
- CI/CD Pipelines: AWS CodePipeline for automated deployment.

Benefits Delivered:

- Successfully modernized and migrated legacy WIPO systems to AWS Cloud, enhancing operational efficiency and scalability.
- Streamlined API creation, maintenance, and security using AWS API Gateway, improving API performance and reducing latency.
- Leveraged AWS Lambda for serverless architectures, reducing infrastructure costs and increasing agility.
- Strengthened system security using AWS IAM policies, safeguarding sensitive data and ensuring role-based access.
- Facilitated cross-team collaboration, leading to smoother cloud transitions and enhanced system performance.

Cognizant Full stack developer

Amsterdam, Netherlands

Jan 2022 - Feb 2024 Full stack software engineer with Java-based frameworks and focusing on AWS cloud technologies.



COGNIZANt* Technologies: Java 17, Spring boot, Hibernate, Docker, Cucumber, JUnit5, Mockito, RESTful, OpenAPI, SOAP, Angular, AWS, Fargate on EKS, RDS for PostgreSQL, CDK by Typescript, IntelliJ, Maven, Git, Jira

Amsterdam, Netherlands

Mar 2022 – July 2023



Full stack developer, Team Lead

The project for Digital Container Shipping Association (DCSA) as full stack developer and team lead from Cognizant. The focus area was to develop API conformance toolkit (CTK) & deploy it on AWS Sandbox.

Technologies: Java 17, Spring boot, Hibernate, Docker, Cucumber, JUnit5, Mockito, RESTful, OpenAPI, SOAP, Angular, AWS, Fargate on EKS, RDS for PostgreSQL, CDK by Typescript, IntelliJ, Maven, Git, Jira

Key Responsibilities:

- Develop CTK and refine the functional requirements with business requirements
- Design and implement the requirements
- Develop microservice & RESTful API
- Participate in Scrum and Agile ceremonies
- Code reviewing in agile team

Benefits delivered:

- Redesigned CTK reporting system.
- Rearchitect CTK from local test runner to microservice.
- Automate/Digitalize support.

Nordea Bank Helsinki, Finland

Mar 2021 – Dec 2021



Full stack developer

The assignment involved online customer service support through the online meetings, chat and issue tracking system. We develop micro service and provided REST APIs that support customer support for digital banking.

Technologies: Java 12, Spring boot, Hibernate, Angular, Docker, Cumber, JUnit, Mockito, RESTful, SOAP, ReactJs, IntelliJ, Maven, Git, Jira.

Key Responsibilities:

- Analyze and refine the functional requirements with business
- Design and implement the requirements
- Develop microservice & RESTful API
- Participate in Scrum and Agile ceremonies
- Code reviewing in agile team
- Encryption & data security solutions

Benefits delivered:

- Enhanced functional requirements analysis and refinement, leading to more precise and effective solutions.
- Successfully designed and implemented business requirements into scalable solutions.
- · Developed robust micro services and RESTful APIs, improving system efficiency and maintainability.
- · Contributed to increased team productivity and project success through active participation in Scrum and Scaled agile ceremonies.
- Ensured high code quality and team alignment thorough code reviews.
- Implemented advanced encryption and data security solutions, significantly enhancing system security and compliance.

Nets Payment Helsinki, Finland

Apr 2020 - Mar 2021



Full stack developer

The assignment involved credit card payment service provided by Nets which is Europe's largest card payment service provider for European banks. My contribution was to reducing payment transaction time by optimizing several SQL, NoSQL databases, and Kafka transactions. Improved audit report feature backend using Java, spring boot, hibernate and frontend by Angular.

Technologies: Java 11, Spring Boot, Hibernate, Docker, OpenShift, Kafka, RabbitMQ, JUnit, Mockito, RESTful, SOAP, Angular 11, MongoDB, Oracle SQL.

Key Responsibilities:

- Technical development.
- Analysis refinement
- Resolve incidents in various environments (prod, dev, test, etc)

Benefits delivered:

- Onboarded several new banks and companies.
- Improved overall payment system.
- Improved audit report feature.

Volvo Cars Gothenburg, Sweden

Jul 2019 - Mar 2020



Full stack developer & Rotating Scrum Master

Full stack development of Volvo's internal tool GCC (Global Car Configurator) to configure a car for production. There were 2 branch production branches that were developed in older Java 1.6. Another enhancement branch which we had to migrate Java 1.6 code to Java 1.8 and upgrade all other related frameworks. GCC was a distributed Spring boot micro service system that communicates with several external components by means of both SOAP and REST. Later migrated to Quarkus-based micro services.

Technologies: Java 6&8, Struts, Spring Boot, Quarkus, ReactJs, Hibernate, EJB, Azure DevOps, JUnit, Mockito, RESTful, SOAP. Redis, Apache Tiles

Key Responsibilities:

- Design, development and maintenance of applications.
- Created and maintained Azure CI/CD pipeline.
- Technical management of project teams and code reviews.
- Configuration management, release process, deployment and delivery.
- Agile Team Management.
- Responsible for mitigating legacy Java 6 to modern Java.
- Migrating Spring Boot micro services to Quarkus-based micro services.
- · Maintaining legacy views by Apache Tiles.
- Migrating from Apache Tiles to ReactJS.

Benefits delivered:

- Improved GCC data caching logic for faster response time.
- Designed and implemented new feature interior room.
- Global GCC users immensely benefited for those improvements.

Ericsson Espoo, Finland



Full stack developer

Full stack development of Ericsson's Device Connection Platform (DCP) connects billions of IoT devices globally, providing scalable, cloud-based solutions tailored to enterprise needs. DCP is built using a microservices architecture deployed on AWS Cloud, with integrated Elasticsearch for real-time search and analytics across vast datasets and Redis for in-memory caching, ensuring high availability, low latency, and robust performance. DCP had several microservices such as Consumer Connectivity (CC), Enterprise Configuration Management (ECM), etc.

Technologies: Java 8, Elasticsearch, Redis, Apache Camel, AWS, GraphQL, Docker, Ansible, IoT, Hibernate, Vaadin, JUnit, Mockito, RESTful, Angular

Key Responsibilities:

- Implemented data bucket definition for CC pods by following TDD, Java 8, SQS, SNS, API Gateway, lambda, DynamoDB, RDS.
- Bucket definition authorization by JWT for ECM pods by TDD, Java 8, SQS, SNS, API Gateway, lambda, DynamoDB, RDS.
- Apache Camel as a integration layer for processing and routing IoT messages.
- Technical management and code reviews.
- Vagrant to Docker migration.
- Configuration management, release process, deployment and delivery.
- Related DCP portal GUI implemented by ReactJs and Vaadin

Benefits delivered:

- Improved DCP service for millions of users worldwide.
- Designed and implemented new features for DCP.
- Because of vagrant to docker migration significant development and QA time were reduced.

Fnx Solutions Helsinki, Finland

Oct 2014 - Apr 2018

Senior Software Engineer

I had to work with several Finnish companies as a consultant from Fnx Solutions.

Technologies: Java 8, Spring Boot/MVC, Struts, Elasticsearch, Redis, Kafka Hibernate, GraphQL, Neo4j, Node.js, Expres.js, Scala, Akka Azure DevOps, Micro service, Liquibase, JPA, JUnit, Mockito, RESTful, SOAP, gRPC, Apache Tiles, Thymeleaf, JSP

Key Responsibilities:

- Building online investment & trading platform https://fasolutions.com/features/
- TV's legacy backend migrated to Azure by Java 8, Spring Boot, Hibernate
- Yle Radio's legacy backend migrated to Azure backend by Java 8, Spring Boot, Hibernate, PostgreSQL.
- Svea's backend legacy backend migrated to Azure by Java 8, Spring Boot, Hibernate, MySQL.
- GameWe developed by Node.js, Express.js. GameWe V2 developed by Scala Akka toolkit.

Benefits delivered:

- Improved FA Solutions investment & trading platform
- Yle TV web service: http://areena.yle.fi/tv
- Improved Yle Radio web service: http://yle.fi/radio/radiosuomi/
- Improved debt recovery service: http://www.svea.com/fi/fin/
- Modernize GameWe social get-together service

Espoo City **Espoo**, Finland

Senior Software Developer

City corporation technologies are part of Espoo city cooperation that takes care of Espoo city construction and maintenance work.

Aug 2013 - Jun 2014



Technologies: .Net, ASP, Android, Azure, Windows Phone, SVN

Key Responsibilities:

- Automatic web service Info TV was implemented by C# ASP .NET
- Implemented Azure cloud-based maintenance management system Solax backend by .Net C#, node.js.
- Implemented Windows Phone 8 and Android App for Solax

Benefits delivered:

- Info TV automatic web service that displays meetings from the Exchange server & news from SharePoint.
- Developed Solax Azure cloud-based maintenance management system.
- Developed Windows Phone 8 App and Android App for Solax and published them in the App Store.



Metropolia University Espoo, Finland

Feb 2011 - Aug 2013



Software Supervisor, Team Lead

Metropolia University of Applied Sciences is the largest University of Applied Sciences in Finland. As software supervisor and project team lead, I was guiding BSc students and contributing few open-source projects.

Technologies: C, C++, Android, Windows phone, Visual Studio, Eclipse, KDevelop, Git, Android Studio

Key Responsibilities:

- C and C++ practical lab instructor.
- R&D project instructor for bachelor students.
- Developed mobile extension for open-source project Lighttwist by C++.
- Inertia R&D project supervisor.

Benefits delivered:

- Lighttwist mobile extension was very useful for Metroplia staff internally.
- Bachelor's degree students gain practical C and C++ knowledge.
- Successfully delivered Inertia R&D project.

Nokia Smart Phone Espoo, Finland

Jun 2006 - Feb 2011



Senior Software Engineer

Nokia had 3 different kinds of smartphones Nokia OS known as Series 40 phone, Symbian phone and Maemo/Meego Linux base OS. I worked for both series 40 and Symbian phones.

Technologies: C, C++, Java, Shell script, Series 40 Phone, Symbian Phone

Key Responsibilities:

- Nokia series 40 Phone SDK development by C, C++ & Java.
- Symbian Phone internal and public SDK development by C, C++ & Java.
- I had to confirm Java Specification Requests (JSR) with Sun Java for SDK's micro JVM release. By running Technology Compatibility Kit (TCK) with multiple iteration to pass all TCK test cases.

Benefits delivered:

- Internal SDK helped Nokia's internal developers to build Nokia phones.
- External SDK helped 3rdparty developers to build apps for Nokia phones.

EVTEK University Espoo, Finland

Mar 2005 - Apr 2006



Research & Development Software Engineer

EVTEK University of Applied Sciences is the largest University of Applied Sciences in Finland.

Technologies: C, C++, Java, Series 40 Phone, Symbian Phone

Key Responsibilities:

- Developed a few R&D Java micro edition phones and Symbian phone apps/games.
- Bachelor thesis in Nokia's R&D project proximity WLAN Ad-hoc networking from Nokia. Because of the innovative solution for this thesis, I was offered a permanent Software developer role at Nokia as well as awarded Nokia's internal IPR for the thesis.

Benefits delivered:

- Successfully delivered proximity WLAN Ad-hoc networking middleware.
- Because of the innovative solution for this project, I was offered a permanent Software developer role in Nokia. Also, I was awarded Nokia's internal IPR for the innovation.

EDUCATION DETAIL —

2018	Master Degree in Computer Engineering, Major Software Engineering
	Metropolia University, Espoo, Finland
2008	Bachelor Degree in Computer Engineering, Major Software Engineering
	EVTEK University, Espoo, Finland
2024	AWS Certified Developer – Associate
2022	ESE (Full Stack Engineer) Accreditation Accomplishment Certificate
2021	AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner Certification
2019	Google Kubernetes Engine GKE training, Helsinki, Finland
2017	Google cloud platform training, Helsinki, Finland
2012	YKI Finnish language B1 certification, Espoo, Finland
2007	Agile scrum methodology certification, Espoo, Finland
Hobbies and interests	Reading books, learning new technologies

LANGUAGES

TECHNICAL SKILLS

FUNCTIONAL SKILLS

Bengali Native

Business

Fluent

Finnish Intermediate

Hindi

English

Intermediate

Business Domains: Telecommunications & Banking

Cloud: AWS, OpenShift, Azure

SQL DB: Oracle, MySQL, MariaDB, PostgreSQL

NoSQL DB: MongoDB, DynamoDB

SCM: Git, SVN

IDE: Eclipse, IntelliJ

PM Tools: Confluence, Azure DevOps

Java: Java 17+, Spring Boot, Spring Hibernate, Java EE, Maven, Spring REST and Batch, Wiremock

Security: SSL, JWT, OAuth

Dev Tools: Postman, Newman, Grafana,

Written and Verbal Communication. Functional and business analysis.

Team player

Rotating Scrum Master

RECOMMANDATIONS

Annemarie de Groot, Engagement Delivery Lead at Cognizant +31 646 43 84 11 Annemarie.degroot@cognizant.com

Alan Broady, Senior Solution Architect at DCSA +31 65 33 23 140 alan broady@dcsa.org

Eero Koskikallio, CEO at NullPointer +358 44 599 0003 eero koskikallio@nullpointer.fi

Linda Iglamyhr, Scrum Master at Volvo Cars, +46 72 371 7927 linda iglamyhr@volvocars.com